A Guide to the Virginia Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs records, 1921-2009
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs records, 1921-2009
The Library of Virginia
44419
5.15 cu. ft. (15 boxes and oversize banner on shelf)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Virginia Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, July 2009.
Biographical Information
The National Business and Professional Women's Club held it's first convention in St. Louis in July 1919 and elected Gail Laughlin as the first president. Virginia was one of the earliest State Federations to affiliate with the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs. In 1919, Dr. Orie Latham Hatcher, Cornelia Adair, Mrs. Geline MacDonald Bowman, Ella Agnew, Katherine Hawes, and Mrs. Beverly B. Munford called the meeting at which the Virginia Federation was formed with the clubs of Richmond, Roanoke, Lynchburg and Danville as it's charter members. Miss Ella Agnew was the first president of the Virginia Federation, serving 1919 to 1920. In 2009, due to declining membership the Virginia Federation dissolved.
Scope and Content
Records, 1921-2009, of the Virginia chapter of the Business and Professional Women, including annual reports, bylaws, correspondence, histories, minutes, newsletters, photographs, programs, and reports. Included are copies of the newsletter, Federation Notes, 1969-2009; minutes; convention photographs, 1929-2000; annual convention programs, 1926-2009; histories of the organization and presidents; membership finances and rosters, 1996-2007; bylaws, certificates of incorporation, and rules handbooks; and emblems and organizational prayer. Similar materials, such as annual reports, can be found in several folders throughout the collection, therefore a thorough cross checking of all folders is necessary to find related materials.
The chronological files, 1968-2009, mainly contain minutes but also included are annual reports, bylaws, correspondence, finances, memoranda, memorial service programs, photographs, and reports. Of note is the correspondence detailing the closure of various chapters of the organization starting in 1999 and the dissolution of the Virginia chapter of the BPW in 2009. These files contain information on the day to day activities of the organization and works accomplished.
Of note are the files for each president of the chapter from 1919 to 1980. Included are annual reports, clippings, convention programs, correspondence, finances, biographies of the presidents, photographs, reports, and resolutions. Also of note are the photographs. 1929-2002, of annual conventions and presidents (found in the President's files). Also included are copies of A History of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc., Volumes I-III.
Contents List
- Annual reports, 1980-1987. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual reports, 1989-1990. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual reports, 1990-1992. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual reports, 1992-1994. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual reports, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annual reports, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Annual reports, 1997-1998. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Annual reports, 1998-1999. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Annual reports, 1999-2000. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Annual reports, 2002-2004. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual reports, 2004-2007. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Bylaws, policies and standing rules handbook 2002. (Box 2, Folder 2a)
- Certificate of Incorporation and Charters, 1952-2001. (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Chapters, Arlington BPW, 1969-1989. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Chapters, Augusta County BPW, 1999. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Chapters, Falls Church BPW, 1996-2006. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Chapters, Loudoun BPW, 1945-1997. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chronological files, 1968-1969. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Chronological files, 1984-1989. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Chronological files, 1990. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Chronological files, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Chronological files, 1992. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Chronological files, 1993. (Box 3, Folder 1a)
- Chronological files, 1994. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Chronological files, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Chronological files, 1996. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Chronological files, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Chronological files, 1998. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Chronological files, 1999. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Chronological files, 2000. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Chronological files, 2001. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Chronological files, 2002. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Chronological files, 2003. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Chronological files, 2004. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Chronological files, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Chronological files, 2006. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Chronological files, 2007. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Chronological files, 2008. (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- Chronological files, 2009. (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Emblem of the BPW, 1937-1962. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Handbooks, Installation ceremony, nd. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- History book, 75th Anniversary Virginia Federation of BPW, 1994. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- A History of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc., Volume I, 1919-1944. (Volume 5)
- A History of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc., Volume II, 1944-1960. (Volume 5)
- A History of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Inc., Volume III, 1960-1994. (Volume 5)
- Membership, 1996-2000. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Membership, 2000-2001. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Membership, 2001-2002. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Membership, 2002-2003. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Membership, 2003-2007. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, Index to. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Newsletters, The Virginia Business & Professional Woman, 1947-1948. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1969-1970. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1971. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1972, 1974. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1975. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1976. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1977-1978. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1979-1981. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1983-1984. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1985-1986. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1987-1988. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1988-1989. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1990-1991. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1992-1993. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1994. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1995-1996. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1997-1998. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 1999-2000. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 2001-2002. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 2003-2005. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 2006-2007. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Newsletters, Federation Notes, 2008-2009. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Pamphlets, ca. 1990-2001. (Box 9, Folder 3a)
- President's Files, Index. (Box 9, Folder 3b)
- President's Files, Profiles Thru The Years, 1919-1945. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- President's Files, Profiles Thru The Years, 1945-1992. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- President's Files, Ella Agnew, 1919-1920. (Box 9, Folder 6)
- President's Files, Geline McDonald Bowman, 1920-1923. (Box 9, Folder 7)
- President's Files, Catherine Wester, 1923. (Box 9, Folder 8)
- President's Files, Elizabeth Foster, 1923-1926. (Box 9, Folder 9)
- President's Files, Sara Royall, 1926-1928. (Box 9, Folder 10)
- President's Files, Laura H. Penn, 1928-1930. (Box 9, Folder 11)
- President's Files, Edna Holmes, 1930-1932. (Box 9, Folder 12)
- President's Files, Hilda Marshall, 1932-1934. (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
- President's Files, Webb Brown Rothwell, 1934-1935. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- President's Files, Elizabeth Ramey, 1935-1937. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- President's Files, Birdie Dodson, 1937-1939. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- President's Files, Lillian M. Johnson, 1939-1941. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- President's Files, Myrtie Sutphin, 1941-1942. (Box 10, Folder 7)
- President's Files, Nina B. Horton Avery, 1942-1944. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- President's Files, Lucile E. Michie, 1944-1946. (Box 10, Folder 9)
- President's Files, Lena R. Cobb, 1946-1947. (Box 10, Folder 10)
- President's Files, Judge Irene L. Pancoast, 1947-1949. (Box 10, Folder 11)
- President's Files, Lettie S. Brockwell, 1949-1950. (Box 10, Folder 12)
- President's Files, Virginia Dave Moore, 1950-1952. (Box 10, Folder 13)
- President's Files, Margaret Ferguson, 1952-1954. (Box 10, Folder 14)
- President's Files, Mary S. Etter, 1954-1956. (Box 10, Folder 15)
- President's Files, Elizabeth M. McKnight, 1956-1958. (Box 10, Folder 16)
- President's Files, Gladys B. White, 1958-1959. (Box 10, Folder 17)
- President's Files, Dorothy V. Allport, 1959-1960. (Box 10, Folder 18)
- President's Files, Nettie Tucker Yowell, 1960-1961. (Box 10, Folder 19)
- President's Files, Gale B. Hounshell, 1961-1963. (Box 10, Folder 20)
- President's Files, Nellie F. Garnett, 1963-1964. (Box 10, Folder 21)
- President's Files, Jane J. Palmer, 1964-1965. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- President's Files, Agnes M. Ames, 1965-1966. (Box 11, Folder 2)
- President's Files, Doris E. Kean, 1966-1967. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- President's Files, Josephine A. Turrentine, 1967-1968. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- President's Files, Prudence O. Tedder, 1968-1969. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- President's Files, Vivian W. Giles, 1969-1970. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- President's Files, Thelma R. Canada, 1970-1971. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- President's Files, Susan S. Reynolds, 1971-1972. (Box 11, Folder 8)
- President's Files, Doris E. Young, 1972-1973. (Box 11, Folder 9)
- President's Files, Lily M. Albert, 1973-1974. (Box 12, Folder 1)
- President's Files, Lillian B. Wodell, 1974-1975. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- President's Files, Louise Whitman, 1975-1976. (Box 12, Folder 3)
- President's Files, Dolly Showalter, 1976-1977. (Box 12, Folder 4)
- President's Files, Marguerite A. Payez, 1977-1978. (Box 12, Folder 5)
- President's Files, Margarette R. Roper, 1978-1979. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- President's Files, Theda T. Fitzpatrick, 1979-1980. (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Programs, Annual conventions, 1960-1985. (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Programs, Annual conventions, 1986-1989. (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Programs, Annual conventions, 1990-1995. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Programs, Annual conventions, 1996-1999. (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Programs, Annual conventions, 2000-2009. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Programs, Fall board meeting and leadership conferences, 1980-1993. (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Programs, Various awards, banquets, and state conventions, 1969-2009. (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Strategic plans, 1986-2000. (Box 13, Folder 8)
- State Leadership Directory, 1999-2000. (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Sheet music, "The Golden Key," 1924. (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Virginia Military Institute, Supreme Court decision, 1991-1996. (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Virginia Military Institute, Supreme Court decision, clippings, 1991-1996. (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Women's Round Table, 1986. (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Women in Transition Task Force, 1986. (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1929. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1934-1937. (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1940s. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1950s. (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1953 August. (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1960s. (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1970s. (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1980s. (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1985 January. (Box 14, Folder 12)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1985 July. (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1986 October. (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1987. (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1988 May. (Box 14, Folder 16)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1988 August. (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1989 May. (Box 14, Folder 18)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1989 August. (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1989 Fall. (Box 14, Folder 20)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1990s-2000s. (Box 14, Folder 21)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1990 June. (Box 14, Folder 22)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1990 September. (Box 14, Folder 23)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1991 August. (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1992 May. (Box 14, Folder 25)
- Photographs, Conventions, 1993 October. (Box 14, Folder 26)
- Photographs, Conventions, 2002. (Box 14, Folder 27)
- Photographs, Slides of Past Presidents, 1919-1988. (Box 14, Folder 28)
- Photographs, Unidentified, ca. 1980-2000. (Box 14, Folder 29)
- Photographs, Karen Keesling Assistant Secretary Air Force, 1988. (Box 14, Folder 30)
- Photographs, Miscellaneous, ca. 1960s. (Box 14, Folder 31)
- Scrapbooks, oversize photographs, and ephemera, 1929-1973. (Box 15)
  Includes scrapbooks, 1965 and 1969; oversize panoramic photographs of state conventions, 1929, 1933, and ca. 1940; and a group photograph on a wooden frame, 1973. Ephemera includes buttons and a VBPW seal embosser.
- Banner of the BPW, Virginia Federation, nd. (Oversize on-shelf)